Guide to the Zena Bailey Sutherland Papers 1953-2003
University of Chicago Library
- Series IV: Correspondence
  - R, 1966-1999, Rabe, Bernice 1973-1976 Radtke, Kay, 1967 Ray, Collin 1985 Rayward, Boyd W., 1981-1990 Rees, Ennis 1968 Renthal, Helen, 1973 Reyes, Denise, 1997 Reynolds, Jean, 1972 Rife, Mary Calletto 1972-1973 Riley, Elizabeth M. 1964-1967 Roberts, Ellen 1978 Robinson, H. Alan 1966 Rock, Virginia 1990 Rockwell, Harlow 1978 Rodman, Bella 1967 Rollins, Charlemae 1972 Rollin, J. 1994 Roman, Susan, 1990 Rose, Karen 1968 Rosenheim, Edward, 1997 Ross, Karyl 1977-1978 Roth, Margaret Ann 1965-1968 Rowell, John, 1973 Rubenstein, Jacqueline, 1995 Rubin, Betsy 1999 Rubin, Caroline Rubin, Linda Rudin, Ellen 1977 Ruff, Martha R. 1992 Runkle, Martin, 1999 Russ, Lavinia Russe, Susan, 1997 Ryan, Rachel 1998-1999 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - S-Sc, 1961-1997, Sackett, S.J. 1967 Sawicki, Norma Jean, 1968 Scherf, Walter 1972 Schein, Herman 1961-1963 Schreyer, Alice, University of Chicago Library, 1993-1997 Schlager, Norma 1981 Schmidt, Judith, 1970 Schulman, Janet 1979 Schwartzberg, Jenny 1994-1996 Scott, Ann Herbert 1990 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Se-Sw, 1961-1997, Selsam, Millicent E. Sendak, Maurice, 1964-1993 Senick, Gerard "Gary" 1978 Setti, Nina, 1980 Sharp, Dolph 1969-1970 Shaw, John M., 1972 Shaw, Spencer Shelley, Sally Swing 1961 Sicherman, Barbara 1977 Silberg, Sophie, 1968 Siegel, Robert 1992 Slepian, Jan 1995 Smith, Dedrick A. 1997 Smith, Howard Jr. 1970 Snyder, Zilpha Keatley, 1968-1978 Society of Children's Book Writers Society of Midland Authors, 1992 Sonnenschein, Hugo F. 1994 Spaulding, Richard M. 1977 Squire, James R. 1965 Stallard, Louise, 1969 Stanek, Lou, 1993 Stanek, Muriel 1969 Stanton, Henry 1972 Stevenson, Dinah 1992 Stewart, Anne B. 1974 Strothman, Wendy J. 1990 Sturges, Daphne, 1968 Sugge, Keith Sullivan, George 1977 Sullivan, Peggy 1976 Sullivan, Zola Jiles 1977 Sutherland, Alec Swanson, Curtis E., 1974 Sweet, Kim, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - T-V, 1964-1996, Taner, Fatima 1990 Taylor, Theodore 1970 Tengen, Sadako Terhune, Joy E. 1993 Ternes, Marge, 1971 Texas Women's University, 1999 Tew, Robin L. 1978 Thompson, James B. 1967 Thompson, Linda L. 1989 Thompson, Vera, 1998 Tibbets, Albert B., 1967 Tomasino, Christine K. 1988 Townsend, John Rowe 1971-1996 Trask, Margaret 1974 Treselt, Alvin 1972 Trestrail, Joanne Trinkner, Charles L. 1964 Troy, Rita 1976 Troyer, Janet, 1968 Tulloch, Allison 1987 Udry, Janice, 1966 University of Chicago Children's Hospital, 1999 University of Chicago, Department of Medicine, 1994 University of Chicago Division of the Biological Sciences, 1994 University of Chicago Hospitals and Clinics, Auxiliary Committee, 1979 University of Wisconsin-Madison, Charlotte Zolotow Fund, 1999 Valen, Felice Holman 1967 Van Hof, Harold, 1968 Van Der Walt, T.B. 1997 Vanek, Edna, 1970 Vardell, Sylvia, 1990 Varner, Velma V. 1960 Veatch, Susan 1972 Vestal, Jeanne 1969 Viereck, Phil, 1966 Virden, Craig 1995 De Vivanco, Maria Luisa Gefaell, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - W-Z, 1960-1996, Wade, Jan Dees, 1977 Wakefield, Jacqueline M. 1976 Walker, Beth 1974 Walker, F., 1974 Walsh, Jean Paton Walsh, Mary, 1971 Watts, Franklin 1960 Webb, Jean Francis 1965 Webb, Kaye, 1970 Webber, Wendy E. 1967 Webster, Donald F. 1977 Wedgeworth, Robert, 1975 Weening, Richard W. 1975 Weiss, Joan Talmage 1967 White, Anitra 1985 Whitney, Alex 1974 Wieke, Mary Alice Willard, Mildred Wilds 1968 Williams, Elinor 1987-1989 Williams, Sallie 1970 Wilson, Beverly, 1985 Winger, Howard H. 1990 Women's Board 1993-1997 Wood, Nancy 1966 Wright, M. Wye, Sara 1968 Yeager, Allan 1979, 1988 Yee, Florence, 1982 Yep, Laurence 1991 Yuill, Phyllis J. 1974 Zalbow, Tziona Zelinsky, Zelda, 1997 Zellner, Agnes 1996 Zitterman, Miriam Zolotow, Charlottle 1966-1976 Zuckerman, Judy 1989 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified correspondents (1 of 2) (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified correspondents (2 of 2) (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Series V: Writings, Speeches and Publications
  - Subseries 1: Books
    - Children and Books, 3rd edition, copy annotated by Zena Sutherland, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Children and Books, 4th edition, correspondence, reviews and promotional material, 1969-1974 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Children and Books, 5th edition, correspondence, reviews and promotional material, 1975-1980 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Children and Books, 6th edition, correspondence, reviews and promotional material, 1979-1981 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Children and Books, 7th edition, correspondence, reviews and promotional material, 1983-1987 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
    - Children and Books, 8th edition, correspondence, reviews and promotional material, 1987-1990 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Children and Books, 9th edition, correspondence, reviews and promotional material, 1994-1997 (Box 11, Folder 8-9)
    - Children and Books, 9th edition, ZS Notes (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Children and Books, 9th edition, Alpha Copy (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Children and Books, 9th edition, Beta Copy (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Children and Books, 10th edition, correspondence, reviews and promotional material, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Children and Books, Compilation of Reviews (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Children and Books, correspondence (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Children and Books, notes (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Children and Books, notes and materials for revisions, 1976-1997 (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
    - The Best in Children's Books, correspondence, reviews and advertisements, 1972-1993 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - The Best in Children's Books, reviews and advertisements, 1973-1979 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Arbuthnot Anthology of Children's Books; Scott-Foresman Anthology of Children's Books, correspondence, 1974-1992 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Children's Literature - An Illustrated History, 1995, correspondence and notes, 1982-1995 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Children's Literature - An Illustrated History, 1995, "American Children's Literature, 1870-1945, chapter drafts, ca 1993 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Children's Literature - An Illustrated History, 1995, "Internationalism, Fantasy and Realism, 1945-1970," chapter drafts, ca 1993 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Children's Literature - An Illustrated History, 1995, "Contemporary Children's Literature, 1970-," chapter drafts, ca 1993 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Children's Literature - An Illustrated History, 1995, galleys, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Children's Literature - An Illustrated History, 1995, galleys, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Children's Literature in the United States (1 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Children's Literature in the United States (1 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Children's Literature in the United States (2 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Children's Literature in the United States (3 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 2: Articles
    - "Books for Young People," Saturday Review, correspondence and clippings, 1966-1973 (1 of 3) (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - "Books for Young People," Saturday Review, correspondence and clippings, 1966-1973 (2 of 3) (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - "Books for Young People," Saturday Review, correspondence and clippings, 1966-1973 (3 of 3) (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Chicago Tribune, photocopies, galleys and typescripts, 1972-1977 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Chicago Tribune, photocopies, galleys and typescripts, 1978-1993 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Chicago Tribune, miscellaneous (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Compton's Encyclopedia, correspondence and typescripts, 1973-1995 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Compton's Encyclopedia, typescripts, 1984-1989 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - World Book Encyclopedia, correspondence and reprints, 1976-2000 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - "Evaluating Books for Children," Illinois Libraries, September, 1961, correspondence and reprint, 1961-1966 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - "R.S.V.P.," Owlet among the Colophons, September, 1967, correspondence and reprint, 1967-1968 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - History in Children's Books, 1967, reviews and advertisements, 1967-1973 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - "Not Another Article On the Newbery-Caldecott Awards?" Top of the News, April 1974, typescript and photocopy, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - "Science as Literature," Library Trends, April 1974, correspondence, typescript and reprints, 1974-1980 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - "Information Pleases - Sometimes," Wilson Library Bulletin, October 1974, typescript, correspondence and clipping, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - "The Children's Book World," typescript, c.1975 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - 'Children's Literature in Education' #22, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - "In Search of the Perfect Picture Book Definition," Wilson Library Bulletin, October, 1977, typescript, correspondence, clipping, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - "Golden Apples and Blue Ribbons, the Meaning of International Awards," Children's Books International 3, 1978, typescript draft and reprint, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - "Science Books are Better Than Ever," American Libraries, October 1981, typescript, clipping and reprint, 1981-1982 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Children in Libraries, 1981, reviews and advertisements, 1981-1983 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - "The Problems of Translating Children's Books," The Role of Literature in Reading Instruction, 1981, correspondence and volume, 1977-1981 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - "The Children's Book World Today," Children's Literature Review 6, 1984, draft and press releases, c. 1984 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - "Children's Books, 1985-1987," Bible Review, Winter 1987, correspondence, typescript and reprint, 1987 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Tribute, Paul and Ethel Heins, manuscript, memorial program, 1997 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Building a Special Collection of Children's Literature in Your Library, 1998, materials and correspondence, 1987-1998 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - "Mildred L. Batchelder, 1901-1998," Horn Book Magazine, January/February 1999, correspondence, manuscript and photocopy, 1998-1999 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - "One Hundred Books That Shaped the Century," School Library Journal, January 2000, correspondence and reprint, 1999-2001 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Reviews, 1973-1977, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Publications and offprints, 1960-1978, "The Center for Children's Books," ALA Bulletin, September 1960 "Selecting Children's Books," University of Chicago Magazine, February 1963 "What's Going On, Anyway? You Want to Buy a Book; You're Overwhelmed, and No Wonder!" Ranally World, December 1966 "Current Reviewing of Children's Books," Library Quarterly, January 1967 "Zena Sutherland Book Reviews - Before and After," School Library Journal, February 1975 "The Center for Children's Books," University of Chicago Library Society Bulletin, Fall 1976 "Realism in Children's Books, has it gone too far?" Modern Realistic Stories for Children and Young People, 1978 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Publications and offprints, "Sutherland Selects Ten Children's Books for Gifts," Chicago Chronicle, December 3, 1981 "Introduction to the Conference," Library Quarterly 51, 1981 "Minority Fiction," Story in the Child's Changing World, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - "Introduction," Island of the Blue Dolphins, 1990, correspondence and typescript, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Orchard Book of Nursery Rhymes, 1990, correspondence, typescript, reviews and advertisements, 1986-1998 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Tribute to Sophie Cousins Silberberg, for USBBY, typescript, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - "John Donovan, An Extraordinary Person, An Extraordinary Writer," manuscript, correspondence and photocopy, c. 1992 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Reader's Companion to Twentieth-Century Children's Literature, correspondence and typescripts, 1992-1994 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Reader's Companion to Twentieth-Century Children's Literature, research materials, undated (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Introduction, Whole Language, Literature, Learning and Literacy - A Workshop in Print, Lou Willett Stanek, 1993, correspondence and typescript, 1992-1993 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Foreword, I Remember, Fara Lynn Krasnopolsky, 1995, manuscript and correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Essay for Chapter 1, Legacies - Using Children's Literature in the Classroom, 1996, correspondence and typescript, 1993 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - "The Newbery at 75, Changing with the Times," American Libraries, March 1997, correspondence, drafts and reprint, 1996-1997 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Writings, Misc. (1 of 2) (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Writings, Misc. (2 of 2) (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 3: Presentations
    - Arbuthnot Host Committee (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Lecture/Talk Correspondence (1 of 2) (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Lecture/Talk Correspondence (2 of 2) (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Lectures, Publications and Publicity (1 of 2) (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Lectures, Publications and Publicity (2 of 2) (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Introduction of Hazel Rochman, typescript, 1989 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Texts of brief presentations, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified ZS Lecture Notes (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 4: Correspondence with Publishers
    - Open Court Publishing Company, 1974-1989 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Orchard Publishing Company, 1988-1991 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - University of Chicago Press, 1965-1976 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1968-2000, Addison-Wesley Publishing Company, 1968 American Library Association, 1988-1997 Bantam Doubleday Dell, 1996 Beacon Press, 1991 Browndeer Press, n.d. Candlewick Press, 1991 Children's Book Council, 1995 Clarion books, 1997 Contemporary Literary Criticism, 1982 DK Ink, 1999 Elsevier/Nelson Books, 1980 Encyclopedia Britannica, 1980 Encyclopedia of Children's Literature, 2000 Fiera del libro per Ragazzi, 1992 Four Winds Press, 1968 Front Street/Cricket books, 1999 Gale Research Company, 1982 Golden Books, 1999 Good News Publishers, 1983 Grolier Enterprises, 1983 Harcourt Brace, 1993 HarperCollins, 1995 Harvard University Press, 1987-1989 Herald House, 1976 Horn Book, 1983-2000 Houghton Mifflin, 1995 Hyperion, n.d. Library Quarterly, 1997 Little, Brown and Company, 1995 Macmillan Publishing Company, 1987 North-South books, 1994 Penguin USA, 1995 Russell Sage Foundation, 1988 St. James Press, 1976-1988 St. Martins Press, n.d. Scholastic, Inc. 2000 Scott, Foresman and Company, 1987 Simon & Schuster Walker and Company, 1996 (Box 20, Folder 8)
- Series VI: Subject and Clipping Files
  - Author Profiles, Ada-Asimov (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Author Profiles, Baker-Byers (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Author Profiles, Caldecott-Crews (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Author Profiles, Dahl-Donald (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Author Profiles, Emberley-Fujikama (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Author Profiles, Gardam-Greene (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Author Profiles, Hall-Quest-Hutchins (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Author Profiles, Isadora-Kurelek (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Author Profiles, Laimgruber-Lowry (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Author Profiles, Macaulay-Mikhalov (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Author Profiles, Barry Moser (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Author Profiles, Nordstrom-Opie (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Author Profiles, Parish-Rogers (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Author Profiles, Scoppettone-Sykes (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Author Profiles, Maurice Sendak (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Author Profiles, Taylor-Vipont (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Author Profiles, Ward-Zolotow (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Awards (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Bibliotherapy (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Book reviews (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Censorship (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Censorship (Box 22, Folder 4-6)
  - Children's books, photocopied excerpts (Box 22, Folder 7-8)
  - Children's books, photocopied excerpts (Box 23, Folder 1-5)
  - Children's literature and publishing (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Children's literature and publishing (Box 24, Folder 1-4)
  - Disability (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Flyers, press releases and other announcements (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Folklore, fantasy and fairytales (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Gender and sexuality (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Illustration (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Language (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Librarianship (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Literary criticism (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Minority groups (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous articles (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Notable Book Lists (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Picture books, articles (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Poetry (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Publishing and Marketing (1 of 2) (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Publishing and marketing (2 of 2) (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Racism in children's literature (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Reading aloud (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Reading and learning (Box 26, Folder 4-5)
  - Reading interests (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Reviewing children's books (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - School libraries (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Science fiction (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Selection and evaluation (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Series books (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Sexism (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Storytelling (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Television (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Textbooks (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Translations (Box 27, Folder 9)
- Series VII: Audio-Visual Materials
  - Rolodex cards (Box 28)
  - Index cards with bibliographical notes (Box 28)
  - Awards (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Slides of book illustrations (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Photographs (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Contents of file box (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Contents of file box (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: VHS of PBS profile of author Valiska Gregory on the show Across Indiana/Production of Gregory's When Stories Fell Like Shooting Stars illustrated by Stephano Vitale (Box 30)
  - Item 2: VHS, 'Sutherland Award 1999' (Box 30)
  - Item 2: Audio recording of "A Place for All Reasons," WEFM, September 13, 1973, with guests Zena Sutherland and Yolanda Federici (Box 30)
  - Item 3: Audio recording, WMAQ-TV NBC Chicago, October 30, 1966, "Read Me a Story" (Box 30)
  - Item 4: Audio cassette of Zena Sutherland's memorial service (Box 30)
  - Item 5: Audio cassette of "Conversations at Chicago," "Evaluating Children's Books" with Zena Sutherland, Yolanda Federici, Marci Carafoli, and Milton Rosenberg (Box 30)
  - Item 6: Audio cassette of "Children, Childhood, and Literature" (Box 30)
  - Item 7: Audio cassette of "Reading Books and Asking Questions" with Zena Sutherland and Jack Fraenkel, produced by The Children's Book Council, Inc. (Box 30)
  - Item 8: Audio cassette, 'William Allen White Banquet, Wichita, KS, 11/1/73 (Box 30)
- Series VIII: Restricted Materials
  - Student recommendation letters (miscellaneous) (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Student grade forms (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Student recommendation letters for employment (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - University Appointment Documents, 1975-1984 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence regarding personnel matters, 1991-1994 (Box 31, Folder 5)